[
  {
    "number": 1,
    "question": "What allele(s) are recessive under this system?",
    "options": [
      "A) A",
      "B) B",
      "C) i",
      "D) A and B",
      "E) B and i"
    ],
    "answer": "C",
    "explanation": ""
  },
  {
    "number": 2,
    "question": "Blood type AB demonstrates what non-Mendelian inheritance pattern?",
    "options": [
      "A) Codominance",
      "B) Complementation",
      "C) Incomplete dominance",
      "D) Linkage",
      "E) Polygenic inheritance"
    ],
    "answer": "A",
    "explanation": ""
  },
  {
    "number": 3,
    "question": "A man heterozygous for blood type A marries a woman heterozygous for blood type B. If they are to have three children, what is the probability that none of the three children are blood type O?",
    "options": [
      "A) 1",
      "B) 3/4",
      "C) 8/27",
      "D) 27/64",
      "E) 1/64"
    ],
    "answer": "D",
    "explanation": ""
  },
  {
    "number": 4,
    "question": "A man of blood type B marries a woman of blood type O. Their first child is blood type O. They plan to have five children. Assuming they will have five children total, what is the probability that three of the children have blood type O and two of the children have blood type B?",
    "options": [
      "A) 1/2",
      "B) 3/8",
      "C) 5/16",
      "D) 5/32",
      "E) 0"
    ],
    "answer": "D",
    "explanation": ""
  },
  {
    "number": 5,
    "question": "Which of the following population traits would cause a shift from Hardy-Weinberg equilibrium?",
    "options": [
      "A) No mutation",
      "B) Random mating",
      "C) Infinitely large population",
      "D) Natural selection",
      "E) No introduction of new alleles"
    ],
    "answer": "D",
    "explanation": ""
  },
  {
    "number": 6,
    "question": "Which of the following could cause increased frequency of recessive disorders?",
    "options": [
      "A) Genetic drift",
      "B) Geographic isolation",
      "C) Reproductive Isolation",
      "D) Heterozygote advantage selection",
      "E) All of the above"
    ],
    "answer": "E",
    "explanation": ""
  },
  {
    "number": 7,
    "question": "For a two allele system, the Hardy-Weinberg equation can be written as: p² + 2pq + q² = 1. What does the term 2pq represent in the Hardy-Weinberg equation?",
    "options": [
      "A) The population of heterozygotes",
      "B) Double the population of heterozygotes",
      "C) The frequency of heterozygotes",
      "D) Double the frequency of heterozygotes",
      "E) The population of all homozygotes in the model"
    ],
    "answer": "C",
    "explanation": ""
  },
  {
    "number": 8,
    "question": "Based solely on the phylogenetic tree to the right, which of the following animals is/are most closely related to the bald eagle?",
    "options": [
      "A) Alligator",
      "B) Antelope",
      "C) Sea bass",
      "D) Lamprey",
      "E) More than one of the above"
    ],
    "answer": "E",
    "explanation": ""
  },
  {
    "number": 9,
    "question": "Based solely on the phylogenetic tree to the right, which of the following animals is/are most closely related to the antelope?",
    "options": [
      "A) Alligator",
      "B) Bald eagle",
      "C) Sea bass",
      "D) Lamprey",
      "E) More than one of the above"
    ],
    "answer": "B",
    "explanation": ""
  },
  {
    "number": 10,
    "question": "Assuming Hardy-Weinberg equilibrium, what must the sum of the alleles, A, B, and i, be equal to?",
    "options": [
      "A) 27/16",
      "B) 9/4",
      "C) 5/4",
      "D) 1",
      "E) 3/4"
    ],
    "answer": "D",
    "explanation": ""
  },
  {
    "number": 11,
    "question": "Assuming Hardy-Weinberg equilibrium, if 1/9 of the population has blood type O and the frequency of B alleles is 1/4. What fraction of the population has blood type AB?",
    "options": [
      "A) 5/12",
      "B) 7/12",
      "C) 5/24",
      "D) 7/36",
      "E) 1/4"
    ],
    "answer": "C",
    "explanation": ""
  },
  {
    "number": 12,
    "question": "If the allele frequencies of allele for a population is A is 0.6, B is 0.2, and O is 0.2, assuming Hardy-Weinberg equilibrium, calculate the percentage of individuals with type A blood?",
    "options": [
      "A) 0.72",
      "B) 0.6",
      "C) 0.48",
      "D) 0.36",
      "E) 0.24"
    ],
    "answer": "D",
    "explanation": ""
  },
  {
    "number": 13,
    "question": "Write out the Hardy-Weinberg equation for the ABO blood group model with respect to the variables A, B, and i. Then identify which term(s) correspond to each phenotype and use them to complete the table. [3.5 points]",
    "options": [],
    "answer": "Equation: (A + B + i)² = 1 OR A² + B² + i² + 2AB + 2Ai + 2Bi = 1\nPhenotype | Hardy-Weinberg Terms\n---|---\nBlood Type A | A² + 2Ai\nBlood Type B | B² + 2Bi\nBlood Type AB | 2AB\nBlood Type O | i²",
    "explanation": ""
  },
  {
    "number": 14,
    "question": "What is the best explanation for the observed ratios for the progeny's phenotype?",
    "options": [
      "A) The dominant allele of Gene H masks expression of A blood type",
      "B) At least one recessive allele from each of the two genes is needed for the blood type A phenotype",
      "C) The homozygous recessive genotype of Gene H masks the expression of A blood type",
      "D) One dominant allele from either of the two genes is needed for the blood type A",
      "E) One recessive allele from either of the two genes is needed for the blood type A"
    ],
    "answer": "C",
    "explanation": ""
  },
  {
    "number": 15,
    "question": "What gene interaction best describes this pattern of inheritance?",
    "options": [
      "A) Additive",
      "B) Dominant epistasis",
      "C) Duplicate genes",
      "D) Non-complementary",
      "E) Recessive epistasis"
    ],
    "answer": "E",
    "explanation": ""
  },
  {
    "number": 16,
    "question": "A member of the F2 progeny has children with an individual with genotype iihh. Some of their children have blood type A while others have blood type O. Which of the following are possible genotypes for this member of the F2 progeny? Select all that apply.",
    "options": [
      "A) AiHh",
      "B) AiHH",
      "C) AahH",
      "D) AAHh",
      "E) AAHH"
    ],
    "answer": "A, B, D",
    "explanation": ""
  },
  {
    "number": 17,
    "question": "For a standard dihybrid cross between two individuals heterozygous for two unlinked, non-interacting genes, which of the following is the classic phenotypic ratio?",
    "options": [
      "A) 1:2:1",
      "B) 9:3:3:1",
      "C) 9:7",
      "D) 9:3:4",
      "E) 12:3:1"
    ],
    "answer": "B",
    "explanation": ""
  },
  {
    "number": 18,
    "question": "Based on the pedigree above, what inheritance pattern(s) is/are possible? Select all that apply.",
    "options": [
      "A) Autosomal dominant",
      "B) Autosomal recessive",
      "C) X-linked dominant",
      "D) X-linked recessive",
      "E) Y-linked"
    ],
    "answer": "A, B, C, D",
    "explanation": ""
  },
  {
    "number": 19,
    "question": "If individual IV-1 is born and expressed the disease, which inheritance pattern(s) is/are possible? Select all that apply.",
    "options": [
      "A) Autosomal dominant",
      "B) Autosomal recessive",
      "C) X-linked dominant",
      "D) X-linked recessive",
      "E) Y-linked"
    ],
    "answer": "A, C",
    "explanation": ""
  },
  {
    "number": 20,
    "question": "If individual IV-1 is born and does not express the disease, which inheritance pattern(s) is/are possible? Select all that apply.",
    "options": [
      "A) Autosomal dominant",
      "B) Autosomal recessive",
      "C) X-linked dominant",
      "D) X-linked recessive",
      "E) Y-linked"
    ],
    "answer": "B, D, E",
    "explanation": ""
  },
  {
    "number": 21,
    "question": "If the rare blood disease followed an X-linked recessive inheritance pattern, individual I-2 could have which of the following genotype(s)? Let X' represent the diseased allele. Select all that apply.",
    "options": [
      "A) XRX'",
      "B) XRX",
      "C) X'X'",
      "D) XRY",
      "E) X'Y"
    ],
    "answer": "A",
    "explanation": ""
  },
  {
    "number": 22,
    "question": "If the rare blood disease followed an autosomal recessive inheritance pattern, individual II-1 could have which of the following genotype(s)? Let r represent the diseased allele. (Hint: review the assumptions in the text above the pedigree figure)",
    "options": [
      "A) RR",
      "B) Rr",
      "C) rr",
      "D) Impossible to determine",
      "E) The pedigree cannot be following an autosomal recessive inheritance pattern"
    ],
    "answer": "A",
    "explanation": ""
  },
  {
    "number": 23,
    "question": "If the rare blood disease follows an autosomal recessive inheritance pattern, what is the probability that individual III-3 is a carrier for the rare blood disorder?",
    "options": [
      "A) 0",
      "B) 1/4",
      "C) 1/2",
      "D) 3/4",
      "E) 1"
    ],
    "answer": "C",
    "explanation": ""
  },
  {
    "number": 24,
    "question": "If the rare blood disease follows an autosomal recessive inheritance pattern, what is the probability that individual IV-1 will be affected by the rare blood disorder?",
    "options": [
      "A) 0",
      "B) 1/8",
      "C) 3/8",
      "D) 1/4",
      "E) 1/2"
    ],
    "answer": "D",
    "explanation": ""
  },
  {
    "number": 25,
    "question": "Organisms with the genotypes AaBBCc and AaBbcc are crossed. Assuming independent segregation and complete dominance for each trait. What is the probability of producing a child that will genotypically resemble either of the parents?",
    "options": [
      "A) 0",
      "B) 1/8",
      "C) 3/8",
      "D) 1/4",
      "E) 1/2"
    ],
    "answer": "D",
    "explanation": ""
  },
  {
    "number": 26,
    "question": "Organisms with the genotypes AaBBCc and AaBbcc are crossed. Assuming independent segregation and complete dominance for each trait. What is the probability of producing a child that will phenotypically resemble either of the parents?",
    "options": [
      "A) 1/4",
      "B) 1/2",
      "C) 9/16",
      "D) 3/4",
      "E) 7%"
    ],
    "answer": "D",
    "explanation": ""
  },
  {
    "number": 27,
    "question": "A diploid organism has three pairs of chromosomes (2n=6). Fill in the following table using the information about this organism. Format your answer as a number (e.g. 6). [6 points]",
    "options": [],
    "answer": "Phase of Mitosis: Prophase (# Chromosomes: 6, # Chromatids: 12), Metaphase (# Chromosomes: 6, # Chromatids: 12), Anaphase (# Chromosomes: 12, # Chromatids: 12), Telophase (# Chromosomes: 12, # Chromatids: 12), End of Mitosis (# Chromosomes: 6, # Chromatids: 6)\nPhase of Meiosis I: Prophase I (# Chromosomes: 6, # Chromatids: 12), Metaphase I (# Chromosomes: 6, # Chromatids: 12), Anaphase I (# Chromosomes: 6, # Chromatids: 12), Telophase I (# Chromosomes: 6, # Chromatids: 12), End of Meiosis I (# Chromosomes: 3, # Chromatids: 6)\nPhase of Meiosis II: Prophase II (# Chromosomes: 3, # Chromatids: 6), Metaphase II (# Chromosomes: 3, # Chromatids: 6), Anaphase II (# Chromosomes: 6, # Chromatids: 6), Telophase II (# Chromosomes: 6, # Chromatids: 6), End of Meiosis II (# Chromosomes: 3, # Chromatids: 3)",
    "explanation": ""
  },
  {
    "number": 28,
    "question": "What stage of meiosis is responsible for Mendel's Law of Segregation?",
    "options": [
      "A) Metaphase I",
      "B) Anaphase I",
      "C) Telophase I",
      "D) Metaphase II",
      "E) Anaphase II"
    ],
    "answer": "B",
    "explanation": ""
  },
  {
    "number": 29,
    "question": "What stage of meiosis is responsible for Mendel's Law of Independent Assortment?",
    "options": [
      "A) Prophase I",
      "B) Metaphase I",
      "C) Anaphase I",
      "D) Metaphase II",
      "E) Anaphase II"
    ],
    "answer": "B",
    "explanation": ""
  },
  {
    "number": 30,
    "question": "What stage of meiosis does crossing over occur?",
    "options": [
      "A) Prophase I",
      "B) Metaphase I",
      "C) Anaphase I",
      "D) Metaphase II",
      "E) Anaphase II"
    ],
    "answer": "A",
    "explanation": ""
  },
  {
    "number": 31,
    "question": "What processes produce diploid cells?",
    "options": [
      "A) Mitosis",
      "B) Meiosis I",
      "C) Meiosis II",
      "D) Mitosis and Meiosis I",
      "E) Meiosis I and II"
    ],
    "answer": "A",
    "explanation": ""
  },
  {
    "number": 32,
    "question": "An XAXB mother and a XY father have a child with Klinefelter syndrome with genotype XBXCY. Assume crossing over does not occur. When and where did non-disjunction occur?",
    "options": [
      "A) Meiosis I of the father",
      "B) Meiosis II of the father",
      "C) Meiosis I of the mother",
      "D) Meiosis II of the mother",
      "E) None of these choices"
    ],
    "answer": "A",
    "explanation": ""
  },
  {
    "number": 33,
    "question": "An XAXB mother and a XY father have a child with Klinefelter syndrome with genotype XBXBY. Assume crossing over does not occur. When and where did non-disjunction occur?",
    "options": [
      "A) Meiosis I of the father",
      "B) Meiosis II of the father",
      "C) Meiosis I of the mother",
      "D) Meiosis II of the mother",
      "E) Multiple of these choices"
    ],
    "answer": "D",
    "explanation": ""
  },
  {
    "number": 34,
    "question": "If 30% of the human genome is adenine bases, what percent of the human genome is made of guanine?",
    "options": [
      "A) 10%",
      "B) 20%",
      "C) 30%",
      "D) 40%",
      "E) 50%"
    ],
    "answer": "B",
    "explanation": ""
  },
  {
    "number": 35,
    "question": "Which of the following is not a way in which RNA's structure differs from DNA?",
    "options": [
      "A) Sugar type",
      "B) Nucleic acids",
      "C) Stability",
      "D) Phosphate group",
      "E) Number of strands"
    ],
    "answer": "D",
    "explanation": ""
  },
  {
    "number": 36,
    "question": "What strand is the bottom strand of DNA? (Hint: think start codon)",
    "options": [
      "A) Antisense",
      "B) Noncoding",
      "C) Coding",
      "D) Template",
      "E) More than one of the above"
    ],
    "answer": "D",
    "explanation": ""
  },
  {
    "number": 37,
    "question": "How many total amino acids would you find in Protein Z generated from this DNA transcript?",
    "options": [
      "A) 9",
      "B) 11",
      "C) 12",
      "D) 13",
      "E) 15"
    ],
    "answer": "A",
    "explanation": ""
  },
  {
    "number": 38,
    "question": "When transcribing the mRNA sequence for our gene, RNA polymerase will read the DNA sequence in what direction?",
    "options": [
      "A) Left to right; 3' to 5'",
      "B) Left to right; 5' to 3'",
      "C) Right to left; 3' to 5'",
      "D) Right to left; 5' to 3'",
      "E) None of the above"
    ],
    "answer": "A",
    "explanation": ""
  },
  {
    "number": 39,
    "question": "If the codon of an mRNA transcript reads 3' ACU 5', what amino acid will be translated?",
    "options": [
      "A) Ile",
      "B) Glu",
      "C) Gly",
      "D) Ser",
      "E) Thr"
    ],
    "answer": "D",
    "explanation": ""
  },
  {
    "number": 40,
    "question": "If a base pair was inserted into our DNA sequence as shown below (bolded red between the third and fourth base pair), which mutation is NOT caused?",
    "options": [
      "A) Frameshift",
      "B) Insertion",
      "C) Nonsense",
      "D) Silent",
      "E) None of the above"
    ],
    "answer": "D",
    "explanation": ""
  },
  {
    "number": 41,
    "question": "If a base pair was substituted into our DNA sequence as shown below (bolded red at the ninth base pair; T>C substitution), what mutation is caused?",
    "options": [
      "A) Frameshift",
      "B) Missense",
      "C) Nonsense",
      "D) Silent",
      "E) None of the above"
    ],
    "answer": "B",
    "explanation": ""
  },
  {
    "number": 42,
    "question": "What area of a gene does the RNA polymerase bind to initiate transcription?",
    "options": [
      "A) Enhancer",
      "B) Promoter",
      "C) Shine-Dalgarno sequence",
      "D) Start codon",
      "E) TATA box"
    ],
    "answer": "B",
    "explanation": ""
  },
  {
    "number": 43,
    "question": "In eukaryotes, translation is initiated by recognition of the 5' mRNA cap. Bacteria lack this cap and instead rely on a purine-rich sequence of mRNA for translation initiation. What is this sequence called?",
    "options": [
      "A) Enhancer",
      "B) Promoter",
      "C) Shine-Dalgarno sequence",
      "D) Start codon",
      "E) TATA box"
    ],
    "answer": "C",
    "explanation": ""
  },
  {
    "number": 44,
    "question": "To study a gene, you hybridize mature mRNA of the gene with denatured DNA of the gene. Viewing the resulting structure you see three R loops and four double-stranded regions (similar to image to the right). What can you conclude?",
    "options": [
      "A) The gene has 0 introns and three exons",
      "B) The gene has four introns and three exons",
      "C) The gene has three introns and three exons",
      "D) The gene has three introns and four exons",
      "E) The gene has three introns and 0 exons"
    ],
    "answer": "D",
    "explanation": ""
  },
  {
    "number": 45,
    "question": "Bacteria lack spliceosomes, relying instead on self-splicing introns. While the specific details are different, the general inputs and outputs are the same. Order the steps (labeled A, B, and C) of self-splicing procedure done by the group II introns in the image below.",
    "options": [
      "A) A→B→C",
      "B) A→C→ B",
      "C) B→C→A",
      "D) B → A → C",
      "E) C→B→A"
    ],
    "answer": "B",
    "explanation": ""
  },
  {
    "number": 46,
    "question": "Another important role of the aforementioned 5' cap in eukaryotes is for facilitating export from the nucleus. Do bacteria export their mRNA from a nucleus? Why or why not? Provide an evolutionary explanation for why bacterial mRNA is or is not exported before translation. [3 points]",
    "options": [],
    "answer": "No, bacteria do not export their mRNA [+0.5] because they do not have a nucleus OR 5' cap [+0.5]\nViable evolutionary explanation such as any of the following [+2]\n• Allows for faster response to environmental stimuli\n• Allows for coupled transcription and translation (polysomes)\n• No selective pressure or benefit from adding increased complexity\n• Bacterial mRNA is short lived\n• Eukaryotes gained mRNA export only after internal membranes developed",
    "explanation": ""
  },
  {
    "number": 47,
    "question": "Sanger sequencing reactions differ from PCR mainly because:",
    "options": [
      "A) Only one primer is used",
      "B) A thermostable polymerase is required",
      "C) They produce exponentially amplified products",
      "D) They use ddNTPs to speed up polymerase activity",
      "E) Primer annealing is not a step"
    ],
    "answer": "A",
    "explanation": ""
  },
  {
    "number": 48,
    "question": "A Sanger chromatogram is the visual output of Sanger DNA sequencing (figure is provided). We obtain a Sanger chromatogram with mixed peaks at a single position for a sample; the rest of the sample is clean. What is the most likely biological explanation?",
    "options": [
      "A) The polymerase randomly misincorporated bases",
      "B) Two primers were used",
      "C) The sample contains a heterozygous genotype",
      "D) The ddNTP concentration was too low",
      "E) An incorrect primer was used"
    ],
    "answer": "C",
    "explanation": ""
  },
  {
    "number": 49,
    "question": "We run a PCR, which yields a strong band at the expected size and a faint band ~150 bp shorter. We repeat the PCR, this time with a higher annealing temperature. The shorter band disappears while the main band remains unchanged. What is the most likely explanation?",
    "options": [
      "A) Polymerase degraded near the end of each cycle",
      "B) The template DNA contained a 150 bp deletion polymorphism",
      "C) The shorter band was formed through low-stringency off-target priming",
      "D) Primer-dimers were formed at low annealing temperature",
      "E) The higher annealing temperature allows the primer to dissociate better"
    ],
    "answer": "C",
    "explanation": ""
  },
  {
    "number": 50,
    "question": "We want to test whether a phenotype results from decreased gene expression (as opposed to loss of protein function). Which approach should we use?",
    "options": [
      "A) CRISPR knockout",
      "B) RNAi knockdown",
      "C) Partial CRISPR interference (CRISPRi) knockdown",
      "D) Hypomorphic allele generated by targeted gene disruption",
      "E) Lentiviral transduction"
    ],
    "answer": "B",
    "explanation": ""
  },
  {
    "number": 51,
    "question": "Assume 500,000 total reads were sequenced, and the five reads provided are representative of the overall proportions. Based on the alignments given, do we assume that this mutation is a variant or an artifact?",
    "options": [
      "A) Variant",
      "B) Artifact",
      "C) Both",
      "D) Neither"
    ],
    "answer": "A",
    "explanation": ""
  },
  {
    "number": 52,
    "question": "Why? Explain with proportions.",
    "options": [],
    "answer": "A consistent majority OR 60% of aligned reads contain A at position 15 OR 40% contain G [+1]\nConsistent majority indicates same mismatch, unlikely to be random error [+1]",
    "explanation": ""
  },
  {
    "number": 53,
    "question": "What might the internal gaps (denoted by dashes -) tell us about the relationship between the reads and reference?",
    "options": [],
    "answer": "indel/mutation [+1.5]",
    "explanation": ""
  },
  {
    "number": 54,
    "question": "Before inserting Gene X into the plasmid, we must choose appropriate restriction enzymes and the correct DNA fragment. For each of the three candidate DNA fragments below (A-C), identify the corresponding restriction enzyme pair. Then, determine which fragment is the best choice for cloning into the plasmid and explain why the other options are less suitable. Explain.",
    "options": [],
    "answer": "Fragment A is BamHI and HindIII [+1], and is the ideal choice because it orients Gene X in the correct position about the promoter AND allows for overhang overlap with plasmid for ligation [+2].\nFragment B is HindIII and EcoRI [+1], but incorrectly orients the Gene about the plasmid [+0.5].\nFragment C is PvuII and SmaI [+1], but blunt end digestion prevents overlap or poor insertion efficiency [+0.5].\nMisidentifications cancel out a correct answer",
    "explanation": ""
  },
  {
    "number": 55,
    "question": "After digesting our insert and plasmid, we purify both using gel electrophoresis. After gel electrophoresis, the following bands are visualized. What factors determine the movement of DNA through an agarose gel? Based on these factors, which DNA band(s) should we excise and purify for ligation? Why?",
    "options": [],
    "answer": "In gel electrophoresis, negative charges flow towards the positive end of the gel [+0.5] and smaller sizes travel faster [+0.5]\nFragment D [+1] because it is the cut insert [+0.5]\nFragment E [+1] because it is the plasmid backbone [+0.5]\nMisidentifications cancel out a correct answer",
    "explanation": ""
  },
  {
    "number": 56,
    "question": "What is the name of this procedure, and how does it work? What is the purpose of LB, ampicillin, X-gal, and IPTG, and how do these components interact with components of our plasmid?",
    "options": [],
    "answer": "Blue-white colony screening [+1]\nLB is the media that bacteria grow on [+1]\nAmpicillin is an antibiotic, bacteria with ampicillin resistance gene can grow [+1]\nX-gal is cleaved by B-galactosidase, producing a blue color [+1]\nIPTG binds to and inhibits LacI repressor, allowing transcription of downstream genes [+1]",
    "explanation": ""
  },
  {
    "number": 57,
    "question": "What do the blue colonies and white colonies indicate? What do these outcomes suggest regarding the success of our transformation and/or plasmid cloning? What are the limitations of this screening, and how could we further validate the success of our cloning?",
    "options": [],
    "answer": "Blue colonies indicate successful uptake of an (ampR) plasmid working lacZ [+0.5]\nWhite colonies indicate successful uptake of an (ampR) plasmid without lacZ [+0.5]\nTransformation was successful in allowing growth compared to the control [+1.5]\nOur cloning successfully interrupted LacZ gene [+0.75], but we do not know how well we inserted the DNA fragment into the plasmid. [+0.75]\nViable explanation to validate our results [+1]\nPCR and Gel electrophoresis to confirm size of the plasmid\nDNA sequencing\nAny other reasonable answer",
    "explanation": ""
  }
]